Languages are often formalized as
sets of strings. Alternatively we can
consider a language to be a type-level
predicate,
that is, a function that maps any string
to a type of proofs that the string
belongs to the language. Each inhabitant
of such a membership type
is an explanation, or parsing. If there
are no inhabitants, then the string is
not in the language.
With this simple idea, we can easily
define the usual building blocks of
languages.
For instance, a string is in the union of
P and Q
when it is in P or in Q, so memberships
are sum types, corresponding to logical
disjunction.
Likewise, membership proofs for language
intersections
are product types, corresponding to
logical conjunction.
As a more interesting example, a string w
is in the concatenation of languages P
and Q exactly when there are strings in
P and Q that concatenate to w.
While precise and elegant, this
definition does not tell us how to
recognize or parse language
concatenations,
since the existential quantification is
over infinitely many string pairs.
Now in case you're not used to Agda, let
me point out a few things.
Bottom and top are the empty and
singleton types.
Logically, they correspond to falsity and
truth.
The type x equals y has a single
inhabitant
when indeed x does equal y and otherwise
is empty.
Sum types are written with the disjoint
union symbol.
Non-dependent product types are written
with the cross symbol.
Dependent product types are written with
the exists symbol.
The puzzle addressed by this paper is
how to bridge
the gap between this non-computational
specification
and correct computable parsing.
Now, here's the plan. First we'll define a
normal form for languages.
The main idea is to use Brzozowski-style
language derivatives
at the level of types, which is to say
propositions.
Next, we'll prove lemmas relating this
language normal form to the usual
building blocks of languages.
So far everything is propositional
rather than computable,
that is, at the level of types rather
than
computational inhabitants of those types.
The next step relates our language
limits to decidable form.
Finally we will apply these insights in
two ways to yield
dual correct parsing implementations.
Remembering that a language is a
function from lists, let's consider each
data constructor for lists,
namely nil and cons.
Nullability of a language is the
proposition that the language contains
the empty string.
The derivative of a language P with
respect to a leading character a
is another language, consisting of the
tails
of those strings in P beginning with a.
The proofs that w is in the derivative
of P
with respect to a are exactly the proofs
that a cons w
is in P. The importance of these
definitions
comes from a simple fact with a simple
inductive proof.
Given a language P and a string we can
successively differentiate
P with respect to the characters in the
string, resulting in a final residual
language.
The original language P contains the
input string
if and only if the residual language is
nullable.
This theorem and its proof are shown in
the lower left corner of the slide.
Agda is quite liberal with names, and in
this case
the name of the theorem is
"ðœˆâˆ˜foldlð›¿",
with no spaces. Note that everything on
this slide
applies not just to languages but more
generally to functions from lists
to anything.
The next step in our plan is to identify
and prove a collection of lemmas
that relate Î½ and Î´ to the standard
language building blocks.
The Î½ lemmas on the left relate types
and are equalities or isomorphisms.
The Î´ lemmas on the right relate
languages and are equalities or
extensional isomorphisms.
Agda proves the equalities automatically
simply by normalization.
The others take a bit of effort. All
proofs
are in the paper's source code.
The style of these lemmas is significant.
Each one reduces Î½ or Î´ of a
standard language construction
to Î½ and or Î´ of simpler
constructions.
The computable implementations that
follow and their full correctness
are corollaries of these lemmas.
Given a language and a candidate string,
we can apply the language to the string
to yield a type of proofs
that the string is in the language.
Now we want to *construct* such a proof or
show that one cannot exist.
We can express this goal as a
decision data type.
A parser for a language is then a
computable function
that maps an arbitrary string to a
decision
about whether the string belongs to the
language.
Isomorphisms appear in the language
lemmas of the previous slide,
so we will need to know how they relate
to decidability.
Fortunately the answers are simple. If
two types are isomorphic,
then a decision for one suffices to
decide the other,
since evidence of each can be mapped to
evidence of the other.
Likewise for extensionally isomorphic
predicates.
While we cannot possibly decide all
predicates,
we can decide some of them, and we can do
so compositionally.
Together with the isomorphism deciders
from the previous slide,
these compositional deciders cover all
of the constructions appearing in the
language calculus lemmas.
For example consider deciding the
conjunction of
A and B. If we have proofs of each,
we can pair those proofs to form a proof
of the conjunction.
On the other hand if we have a
disproof of ether we can use it to
construct a disproof of the conjunction.
Let's now pause to reflect on where we
are in the story.
The language decomposition theorem
reduces membership to a succession of
derivatives
followed by nullability. Our language
lemmas
tell us how to decompose nullability and
derivatives of languages
to the same questions on simpler
languages.
The resulting questions are all
expressed in terms of propositions and
predicates
that happen to be compositionally
decidable.
It looks like we're done: we just
formulate the languages,
compute derivatives and nullability, and
apply the language lemmas.
However, we cannot simply apply the
language lemmas by pattern matching,
because languages are functions and so
cannot be inspected structurally.
What can we do? Exactly this
same situation holds in differential
calculus,
since differentiation in that setting is
also defined on functions,
and we have a collection of lemmas about
derivatives for various formulations of
functions,
such as sums, products, transcendentals,
and compositions. When we want to compute
correct derivatives, there are two
standard solutions,
known as "symbolic" and "automatic"
differentiation.
Symbolic differentiation represents
functions structurally
and applies the differentiation rules by
pattern matching.
Automatic differentiation represents
differentiable functions as functions
that compute their derivatives
in addition to their regular values.
We can apply these same strategies to
languages.
Applying the first strategy to languages
leads to an inductive data type of
regular expressions.
To keep a simple and rigorous connection
to our original specification,
let's index this inductive data type by
the type level language
that it denotes. Here I have kept the
vocabulary the same,
distinguishing type level language
building blocks by a module prefix
that appears here as a small lower
diamond.
Note that Î½ and Î´ here are
decidable versions.
Correctness of parsing is guaranteed by
the types of these two functions,
so any definitions that type-check
will suffice.
Given our inductive representation, we
need only define
Î½ and Î´. The definitions shown on
this slide
are systematically derived from the
language lemmas shown earlier in the
talk
using the compositional deciders.
The definitions are to be read in column-
major order,
that is, each column is one definition,
given by pattern matching.
Applying the second strategy to
languages leads
instead to a coinductive type of tries,
which is an exact dual to the inductive
structure of regular expressions.
The language operations are now defined
functions instead of constructors,
while Î½ and Î´ are now selectors
instead of defined functions.
Again, correctness of parsing is
guaranteed by the types,
so any definitions that type-check will
suffice.
Given our coinductive representation, we
need only define the language building
blocks.
The definitions shown on this slide are
also systematically derived from the
language lemmas shown earlier in the
talk,
using the compositional deciders.
This time, the definitions are to be read
in row-major order,
that is, each row is one definition and
is given by co-pattern matching.
Remember that this language
representation is a pair of a Î½ and a
Î´,
so a single definition gives both.
Now here's the magical thing.
Compare this implementation with the
previous one.
The code is exactly the same,
but its interpretation changes, as
signified by the syntax coloring,
which the agda compiler generates during
typesetting.
What pleases me most about this work.
Well, there are three things.
First, there is the simple formal
specification,
uncomplicated by computability.
Second, the clear path of reasoning from
propositionally-defined languages
to decidable parsing via decision types.
Finally, there's the duality of regular
expressions and tries,
paralleling symbolic and automatic
differentiation,
using exactly the same code for parsing
in both cases,
though with dual interpretations.
There are more goodies in the paper. I
encourage you
to give it a read.